Welcome back for probably a very short video.
So, I want to try out something; on one hand, I
had these problems (yesterday) with my setup, that
the interactive buffer was always slowing down,
which I usually don't have on my local machine,
but somehow during the recording it occurs,
so I want to try something else as a test.
And at the same time, there are two or
three things more that I wanted to say
about QuickCheck, and that I forgot
in the other short video before.
So, let me use this opportunity.
Okay, so recap.
We had this sorting function, which
was first incorrect, and we fixed it.
And we had these equations for
expressing properties of this function.
And I talked about this paradigm shift not
only in programming but also in testing.
So, instead of writing unit tests,
the declarative approach of Haskell
encourages thinking about equations, because
everything is an expression, so we can
express behavior or semantics of our
program by talking about equations.
And so it's good practice to, instead of just
writing unit tests, write down properties in the
form of equations, and then have, for example,
QuickCheck or other tools try to populate the
input data with random choices, for example,
and then check that these properties hold.
And we also saw that we get counterexamples
if some property does not hold.
One thing I didn't show
before was how to interpret,
or how the output will look like if you have
more than one thing over which you quantify.
Right, I showed some
examples of these properties.
And when they failed, we got the input
list that made the property fail.
But I didn't show you what happens, or how it
is to be seen if we have more than one input.
And that might be relevant,
because you might also have to write
functions of several parameters.
And then you also have to be able to interpret
a counterexample with more than one input value.
Okay, so that's one thing I want to show.
And first, I'm not doing this
by making a bug in the program,
I'm actually going to do this by
simply introducing a wrong property.
So, let's take this last property; I could run all
the properties now and the check would be okay.
But let me somehow destroy the last line
to write something that is nonsense.
So, if I now run this, I should
get that there is a counterexample.
Okay, let's do this.
Let's call the interpreter here.
And let's run the test suite.
Then first, we have several things that are okay.
Right, you see this, the first four
properties are okay; they all pass 100 tests.
And then we see a "Failed".
It says that it failed after
three tests and two shrinks,
we'll also look at what the shrinking means here.
But let's first interpret the outcome.
And what do we get?
Here we get two lists.
And that corresponds to the fact that
this property that is failing has
two input values, xs and ys.
The way to interpret this here
as a counterexample, right, is
that the first thing that is printed is
the first parameter from the property.
And the second thing is the second,
probably different argument.
When you see something like this, it means
xs equals the empty list [], ys equals
this list, [1,0], violates this property.
And indeed, if you were to now run the left-hand
side and the right-hand side of these two
input data here, we would see
that they are not the same thing,
because the sorting function is
correct, but this property is nonsense.
Okay, so this was one thing I wanted to
show, simply how this has to be interpreted.
Then about the shrinking, how
can we see what happens here?
I mentioned before that QuickCheck always
tries to find small counterexamples.
So, even if the first example it finds
is bigger, it tries smaller ones,
because first it starts with random data.
So, the hope is, for QuickCheck and also for the
users that you get meaningful small counterexamples,
because they are usually better for debugging.
So, once you have a violation of a
property, you want to know what is wrong.
Is the property wrong?
Is the program wrong?
And attach more data for this.
And you can see this in action if you
replace quickCheck again with verboseCheck,
because then we will see what exactly was tested.
Here, let me make this a bit bigger and where
maybe in this case we didn't see much shrinking,
because actually, by happenstance, the first
thing that was found as a counterexample
is already a very small case.
But that was random luck.
So, let's try this again.
And then, for example, we see if we go back,
that the first right here, for example,
the first thing, the first input pair
that failed the property was this one,
which was obtained by random sampling.
Okay.
And then this is something that
QuickCheck could also have already shown:
the property is wrong for these two inputs.
Of course, this would maybe take a bit
too much thinking to see what's wrong.
So, actually, QuickCheck is now trying
to find a smaller counterexample.
So, for example, you see here in the next
step apparently it simply tried, well,
what if I replaced the first list with the
empty list; is it still a counterexample?
And this also failed.
So, now QuickCheck will use
this as a counterexample.
Then it tries, well, maybe I can also make the
second list into an empty
list, it will still fail.
So, next, try this.
But this, unfortunately, passed.
So, this is not a good counterexample.
So, this so far is the best
counterexample that QuickCheck has found.
And well, then try some other things.
So, for example, it tries this list, but this also
passes; then it tries this list, but—and this—,
yeah right, shortens this but it then tries
the second half of this list, but this passed,
So it tries the first half of the list; this
failed, so it is the new best counterexample.
And then it tries again to make this smaller,
so empty list, empty list
actually has been tested before.
So, of course, it passes again, then tries maybe if
I make it, it takes the second part of this list,
but it also passes, so it cannot be a
small counterexample, et cetera, et cetera.
So then the system tries-
What other ways could I
make this example simpler?
So apparently it tried to, instead of
minus one, what if I use just one.
Is it still a counterexample?
Yes, it is.
And then probably also tries
to get rid of the minus three.
And at some point, it
realized, well, [0,3] passes.
So this is not a counterexample.
But minus two also fails, et cetera.
And then at some point,
QuickCheck decides, well,
this is the smallest counterexample I can find,
the smallest in the sense that it is a short list,
at least the first is empty, and the
second one has only two elements.
And it also has tried to make the
values small; it couldn't take zero
and one because that would have passed,
but it can take zero and minus one.
And that somehow is the conceptually
smallest counterexample to the property
that we claimed but was wrong.
And of course, usually, you don't see all
these immediate steps because we use
quickCheck instead of verboseCheck.
But well, at least in these
points, you can see how hard
QuickCheck has tried to
find a small counterexample.
So it didn't encounter this first pair of lists,
which each had four elements after five tests,
and then it performed several shrinkings,
and ultimately, it reached this
as its best counterexample.
And this will be shown then, for
example, in order to if one of your
functions violates a property
that we expect of your solution.
Okay.
And of course, I wouldn't actually
write this wrong property here.
So let me go back to the correct
property, and then you can check it.
This one is, of course, correct.
I have to reload, of course.
Then I run it.
And this is correct again.
But now you also know how these counterexamples
come about and are presented to
you inside the tool, for example.